<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>Calvin&#x27;s Blog</title>
    <link href="https://calvintan.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://calvintan.github.io" />
    <updated>2023-10-02T22:35:14+08:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Calvin</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://calvintan.github.io</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Design Faster: 10 Figma Tips for Designers</title>
        <author>
            <name>Calvin</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://calvintan.github.io/design-faster-with-figma-16-tips-for-designers/"/>
        <id>https://calvintan.github.io/design-faster-with-figma-16-tips-for-designers/</id>
        <media:content url="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/7/cover-4.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="figma"/>

        <updated>2023-10-02T22:35:14+08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/7/cover-4.jpg" alt="Article cover" />
                    Have you ever had those moments in Figma where you feel like you're moving in slow motion, clicking through layers&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/7/cover-4.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Article cover" /></p>
                <p>Have you ever had those moments in Figma where you feel like you're moving in slow motion, clicking through layers and components, knowing deep down that you can work faster and smarter? We've all experienced those pangs of frustration, realizing there's room for improvement.</p>
<p>In this concise guide, I've curated 10 practical tips to elevate your efficiency in Figma. Whether you're just starting your journey or aiming to sharpen your skills, these insights will smooth out your design process.</p>
<h2>1. Select an element with one click</h2>
<p>Here is a typical scenario. To adjust a single object that is nested deep inside of a component, you end up clicking endlessly through each layer to select this element.</p>
<p>Do this instead: Click on the object while holding <code>⌘cmd</code>, and you'll be able to select the object with one click! This is also known as a "deep select".</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/7/tip-1.gif" alt="" width="800" height="450"></figure>
<h2>2. Select several layers</h2>
<p>Do you need to selectively edit several objects in a component? Hold <code>⌘cmd + ⇧shift</code> and click on each object. Mis-clicked an object? Simply click on it again to deselect it.</p>
<h2><figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/7/tip-2.gif" alt="" width="800" height="450"></figure></h2>
<h2>3. Select children or parent layers</h2>
<p>When objects are nested inside a frame or group, the frame layer is called the "parent" and the layers inside are called the "children". We can click on the parent layer and press <code>↩return</code> to select all of the children layers.</p>
<p>Pressing <code>⇧shift + ↩return</code> (or the <code>\</code> key) does the opposite and selects the parent layer. I use these shortcuts frequently when modifying the contents of a table. First I will click on the desired table column, press <code>↩return</code> to select all the cells of that column, and modify all of them at once!</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/7/tip-3.gif" alt="" width="800" height="480"></figure>
<h2>4. Select sibling layers</h2>
<p>Children objects are called "siblings" of each other, and we can select sibling layers too. Press <code>tab</code> to select the first sibling layer, and press <code>tab</code> again to select the next sibling layer. You can also press <code>⇧shift + tab</code> to select the previous sibling layer.</p>
<p>You can now navigate up and down the Layers panel with just your keyboard!</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/7/tip-4.gif" alt="" width="800" height="480"></figure>
<h2>5. Collapse all layers</h2>
<p>Your Layers panel will start to get untidy as you are busy editing objects, leaving a trail of "unfolded" layers. Pressing <code>⌥option + l</code> will collapse the layers back into a neat stack.</p>
<p>Using this shortcut regularly will ensure your Layers panel is kept tidy at all times, making it easy to sift through to find any layer.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/7/tip-5.gif" alt="" width="480" height="540"></figure>
<h2>6. Duplicating objects</h2>
<p>There are several ways to duplicate an object, choose the method that best suits you!</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: lower-alpha;">
<li>Copy and paste the object in place by using <code>⌘cmd + c</code> and <code>⌘cmd + v</code>. Alternatively <code>⌘cmd + d</code> does the same thing by pressing just 1 shortcut.</li>
<li>Click and drag the object while holding <code>option</code>. You can also drag while holding both <code>option + shift</code> create a duplicate along the horizontal or vertical axis.</li>
</ol>
<h2><figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/7/tip-6.gif" alt="" width="800" height="450"></figure></h2>
<h2>7. Add multiple images</h2>
<p>Need to add multiple pictures into your design? <code>⌘cmd + ⇧shift + k</code> is your go-to shortcut to add images in bulk. Select your image files after pressing the shortcut, then click to place them on the canvas or on an object.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/7/tip-7.gif" alt="" width="800" height="450"></figure>
<h2>8. Crop an image</h2>
<p>There is no need to crop an image from the Design panel. Hold <code>⌘cmd</code> and drag on the edge of that image to crop an image quickly. This not only works well with images, but also with frames! Just remember to tick the <strong>clip content</strong> option in your frame.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/7/tip-8.gif" alt="" width="800" height="450"></figure>
<h2>9. Copy and paste properties</h2>
<p>You might want to reuse styles that you've applied to an object or layer. Copy styles by pressing <code>⌘cmd + option + c</code>. Then select the other objects, and press <code>⌘cmd + option + v</code> to paste.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/7/tip-9.gif" alt="" width="800" height="450"></figure>
<h2>10. Copy and paste properties from the Design panel</h2>
<p>A bonus tip: you can copy a style by clicking on the left edge of a fill, an effect, or even a prototype interaction! Once it is selected (highlighted in blue), you can copy and paste onto any layer to apply the same style.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/7/tip-10.gif" alt="" width="480" height="540"></figure>
<hr>
<p>Thank you for exploring these first 10 valuable Figma tips in this article. I hope you've found them helpful in enhancing your design workflow.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for part 2 of this series, where you'll discover another set of 10 essential tips to take your Figma skills to the next level. Keep an eye on upcoming articles as more insights and tools to empower your design journey are on the way.</p>
<p>Also, please leave a comment with your suggestions for future article topics or any questions you might have. Happy designing!</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Design Tokens: Bridging the design-to-code gap</title>
        <author>
            <name>Calvin</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://calvintan.github.io/design-tokens/"/>
        <id>https://calvintan.github.io/design-tokens/</id>
        <media:content url="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/blog-tokens-cover.jpg" medium="image" />

        <updated>2023-02-04T01:53:42+08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/blog-tokens-cover.jpg" alt="" />
                    When I first heard about Design Tokens, I was slow to look into it. However after I finally got started&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/blog-tokens-cover.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p>When I first heard about Design Tokens, I was slow to look into it. However after I finally got started picking it up, I immediately regretted not learning about it sooner.<br><br>I believe that design tokens play an important role in bridging the design-to-code gap. It can help to improve the collaboration between designers and developers, and keep the design of websites or apps aligned with the specifications of a design system.<br><br>I'll go over what a design token is and the benefits of adopting design tokens.</p>
<h2>What is a design token</h2>
<p>Imagine that you have this button component in your design system.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/blog-tokens-1.jpg" alt="" width="1280" height="720" sizes="(min-width: 37.5em) 1600px, 80vw" srcset="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-1-xs.jpg 384w ,https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-1-sm.jpg 600w ,https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-1-md.jpg 768w ,https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-1-lg.jpg 1200w ,https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-1-xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<p>(Without peeking ahead)</p>
<p>Try to visualise this button broken down into the various atoms – as in Atomic Design. Try to make a guess of all the properties that make up this button. Scroll down once you're ready!</p>
<p>...</p>
<p>...</p>
<p>...</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/blog-tokens-2.jpg" alt="" width="1280" height="720" sizes="(min-width: 37.5em) 1600px, 80vw" srcset="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-2-xs.jpg 384w ,https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-2-sm.jpg 600w ,https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-2-md.jpg 768w ,https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-2-lg.jpg 1200w ,https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-2-xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<p>So, did you guess correctly?</p>
<p>These properties and values that make up this button are the <strong>design decisions</strong>.</p>
<p>Of course, the button will not be the only component in your design system. There will be design decisions made for the other components in your design system as well.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/blog-tokens-3.jpg" alt="" width="1280" height="720" sizes="(min-width: 37.5em) 1600px, 80vw" srcset="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-3-xs.jpg 384w ,https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-3-sm.jpg 600w ,https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-3-md.jpg 768w ,https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-3-lg.jpg 1200w ,https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-3-xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<p>Here is a list of possible properties that you might use in your design system. From colors, fonts, spacing and even the animation properties.</p>
<p>You can store these properties and values in the form of a <strong>design token</strong>. A token is basically a key-value pair. This is the same button from before, and beside it I have expressed it's properties and values as JSON.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/blog-tokens-4.jpg" alt="" width="1280" height="720" sizes="(min-width: 37.5em) 1600px, 80vw" srcset="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-4-xs.jpg 384w ,https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-4-sm.jpg 600w ,https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-4-md.jpg 768w ,https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-4-lg.jpg 1200w ,https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-4-xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<p>I hope that my visual example has helped you make sense of what a design token is. Let's also see how others have described a design token:</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/blog-tokens-quote.jpg" alt="" width="1280" height="720" sizes="(min-width: 37.5em) 1600px, 80vw" srcset="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-quote-xs.jpg 384w ,https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-quote-sm.jpg 600w ,https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-quote-md.jpg 768w ,https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-quote-lg.jpg 1200w ,https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-quote-xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/blog-tokens-5.jpg" alt="" width="1280" height="720" sizes="(min-width: 37.5em) 1600px, 80vw" srcset="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-5-xs.jpg 384w ,https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-5-sm.jpg 600w ,https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-5-md.jpg 768w ,https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-5-lg.jpg 1200w ,https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-5-xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<h2>Why should we use design tokens</h2>
<p>To answer this, let's take this example of the design handoff process.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/blog-tokens-6.jpg" alt="" width="1280" height="720" sizes="(min-width: 37.5em) 1600px, 80vw" srcset="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-6-xs.jpg 384w ,https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-6-sm.jpg 600w ,https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-6-md.jpg 768w ,https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-6-lg.jpg 1200w ,https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-6-xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<p>In this scenario, assume that the design – be it a web application or app – is already live. The client wants to make changes, perhaps because of a rebrand, wants to make changes to the colours and fonts etc.</p>
<ol>
<li>The designer makes the desired changes to the UI in the Figma file.</li>
<li>Once the changes have been reviewed and approved, the designer prepares the design specs (e.g. add redlines, annotation and design documentation)</li>
<li>The designer then books a meeting with the developer to communicate these changes and share the specs.</li>
<li>The developer takes over from here. They review the specs and start to write the necessary code according to the updated designs.</li>
</ol>
<p>This entire process repeats for every new change that comes along.</p>
<p>As you can imagine, there is alot of communication for what may be considered "simple changes". Here are three ways that a design tokens approach may help:</p>
<h3>Allow designers to push changes</h3>
<p>A design tokens approach can enable designers to initiate changes from Figma. For example: the designer can push the changes from Figma to the project repository. This in turn allows the developer to retrieve the changes and make the updates seamlessly.</p>
<p>This approach may help to reduce lengthy discussions between designers and developers when sharing specs. This will also prevent the error of copying the wrong values to code.</p>
<h3>Output styles for any platform</h3>
<p>In our example scenario, you may be picturing a single website or app. But what if our client has many platforms – imagine multiple websites, an iOS and Android app – that all need to be updated?</p>
<p>This can be solved by using a token transformer, which allows the developer to output styles in the correct format needed (e.g. CSS, Sass, JS, XML etc) for that platform, saving them a lot of effort.</p>
<h3>A single source of truth</h3>
<p>You may also work with a team of designers who all have edit access to the same design file. Is there a way to keep track of what has changed and why it has changed?</p>
<p>Design tokens can be combined with a version control tool, such as Github, in order to provide a source of truth. Every change can be tracked, and a description of the change can be provided too.</p>
<h2>A design tokens pipeline</h2>
<p>This flow diagram demonstrates what a design tokens approach might look like:</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/blog-tokens-7.jpg" alt="" width="1280" height="720" sizes="(min-width: 37.5em) 1600px, 80vw" srcset="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-7-xs.jpg 384w ,https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-7-sm.jpg 600w ,https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-7-md.jpg 768w ,https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-7-lg.jpg 1200w ,https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/6/responsive/blog-tokens-7-xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<ol>
<li>Following the example scenario, the designer has updated the colours and fonts. There are plugins (e.g. <a href="https://tokens.studio/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer">Tokens Studio</a>) available to help create design tokens and push them to the project repository.<br><br></li>
<li>Once pushed to the project repository, the developer can pull the token file and start to transform them to the correct format needed.<br><br></li>
<li>The transformed file can then be delivered to the various platforms.</li>
</ol>
<hr>
<p>As illustrated in the above scenario, I believe that adopting a design tokens approach will save designers and developers time and effort and improve collaboration.</p>
<p>In a follow-up article, I will include a demo of how this process works in practice.</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>5 tips on improving as a designer</title>
        <author>
            <name>Calvin</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://calvintan.github.io/5-tips-on-improving-as-a-designer/"/>
        <id>https://calvintan.github.io/5-tips-on-improving-as-a-designer/</id>
        <media:content url="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/2/personal-growth.png" medium="image" />

        <updated>2022-11-20T15:21:08+08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/2/personal-growth.png" alt="Personal Growth" />
                    I recently received a question from my mentee on “how to get better as a designer” and “key skills to&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/2/personal-growth.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Personal Growth" /></p>
                <p>I recently received a question from my mentee on “how to get better as a designer” and “key skills to work on”. Here are excerpts of the 5 tips that I shared.</p>
<h3 id="observe-what-others-are-doing-better-than-you">Observe what others are doing better than you</h3>
<p>I’m sure that in your team, there were moments that you were impressed by something your teammate does. “He presented his ideas really well!” or “How does she design all these screens so quickly?”</p>
<p>This hints on the skill that you may want to work on. For example, it could be how to <strong>better articulate your ideas and design decisions</strong> or to <strong>improve your design workflow</strong>.</p>
<p>Next, you can either:</p>
<ol>
<li>Have a chat with them, and ask them for tips or advice</li>
<li>Get together with your team or manager to organise learning sessions</li>
<li>Do your own research, look up books or tutorials on the subject matter</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="ask-for-feedback-early">Ask for feedback early</h3>
<p>Share drafts of your design work early, even if it’s rough. This will help improve your ability to articulate your ideas, which is crucial for any designer.</p>
<p>You might be thinking: “But it looks terrible! Won’t this reflect poorly on my design ability?” I feel that sharing your work early has the opposite effect. It makes you seem proactive, and it’s what you should be doing in order to find the right solution.</p>
<p>It also tests if you can explain your design decisions clearly to another team member,  helps to find any potential gaps in your thinking, and clarifies your understanding of the problem that you’re trying to solve.</p>
<h3 id="set-goals">Set goals</h3>
<p>In my current team, each of us are encouraged to set a monthly goal to work on. We will also have to demonstrate proof that we are actually keeping to it (or face a “penalty” – like buying everyone coffee 😛)</p>
<p>I’m sure this feels like you’re being forced to do it. But it’s not necessarily a bad thing as this approach does help you to build a habit and holds you to that commitment.</p>
<p>Consider commiting to a manageable goal and sharing it with your team. This could be something like: “Read one design book per month and share what your learnt”.</p>
<h3 id="work-on-a-side-project-that-youre-passionate-about">Work on a side project that you’re passionate about</h3>
<p>Ever had a new year’s resolution where you told yourself “I’ll master (insert the supposed thing) this year!” but it never materialised? The problem may stem from the fact that you haven’t broken it down into enough actionable steps.</p>
<p>First, it should be something that will motivate you to work on it everyday. To the extent that it is top-of-mind in your daily todos, otherwise you might stop doing it after awhile. On top of that, it should be <em>actionable enough</em>, like “read one chapter of a book per week” and not “finish reading encyclopedia in 1 hour”.</p>
<p>It may also help to pick an area that is relevant to your work, so you get to put it into use immediately. For example, I could start a project to pick up 3D, but it is a skill that I can’t apply regularly at work. That would cause me to lose motivation and gradually lose interest.</p>
<h3 id="teach-others">Teach others</h3>
<p>I believe that in order to teach a topic, you first need to have a solid understanding of that topic. Teaching is not something where one can jump in and simply <em>wing it</em>.</p>
<p>If you can explain a particular topic simply, clearly and well to others, this means that you have a good grasp of it. </p>
<p>For example, pretend to be teaching any design topic to your team. Are you able to explain it well enough? If the answer is “no” then it’s a signal to do some light research, read books or articles on the topic and try again. Doing this will solidify your understanding of the topic.</p>
<h3 id="closing-thoughts">Closing thoughts</h3>
<p>Up to this point in my career, I never had a design mentor as I was mostly working as a “team of one” designer. This always made me anxious about not keeping up to date or if there were skills that I should be picking up (FOMO 😅).</p>
<p>What I’ve been practicing is to “be the mentor you wish you had”, to serve as my motivation to stay ahead of the curve and do my best work everyday.</p>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>&quot;First commit&quot;</title>
        <author>
            <name>Calvin</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://calvintan.github.io/first-commit/"/>
        <id>https://calvintan.github.io/first-commit/</id>
        <media:content url="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/1/abstract-plant-growth.png" medium="image" />

        <updated>2022-11-20T15:21:03+08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/1/abstract-plant-growth.png" alt="Growth" />
                    Like all my coding projects, the first thing I would do is: start a Github repository, add all the base&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://calvintan.github.io/media/posts/1/abstract-plant-growth.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Growth" /></p>
                <p>Like all my coding projects, the first thing I would do is: start a Github repository, add all the base files and push the “first commit” to Github.</p>
<p>This is my first commit to this blog, and it marks my “commit”ment to make writing a habit. I’m not exactly sure what this blog will contain yet, but I’ll start penning down some thoughts and see how it grows from there.</p>
<p>If you’re passing by, feel free to stop and say “hello”. Hopefully this space will be populated with more interesting articles soon! Till next time 👋</p>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
